<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on utsav shukla</title>
    <link>//localhost:1313/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on utsav shukla</description>
    <image>
      <title>utsav shukla</title>
      <url>//localhost:1313/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</url>
      <link>//localhost:1313/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.134.0</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 05:05:54 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="//localhost:1313/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Ns</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/ns/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 05:05:54 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/ns/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;numerical-instability-of-softmax&#34;&gt;Numerical Instability of Softmax&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Softmax function is widely used in machine learning, especially for converting raw scores (logits) into probabilities in classification problems. It is defined as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Softmax(z_i) = exp(z_i) / sum(exp(z_j) for j in range(n))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;where &lt;code&gt;z_i&lt;/code&gt; represents the logits for class &lt;code&gt;i&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-problem-of-numerical-instability&#34;&gt;The Problem of Numerical Instability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Softmax function can suffer from &lt;strong&gt;numerical instability&lt;/strong&gt;, particularly when the input logits &lt;code&gt;z&lt;/code&gt; contain large or small values. This is because computing &lt;code&gt;exp(z_i)&lt;/code&gt; can result in very large or very small numbers, leading to overflow or underflow errors when summed across all classes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>blockbuster</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/blockbuster/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 04:21:35 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/blockbuster/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;recently, while watching the music video for faris shafi&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-urTPhh7gNk&#34;&gt;blockbuster&lt;/a&gt;, i noticed something interesting. the song was in punjabi, but the subtitles (and even the hoardings and other text) on the screen were in the arabic script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it struck me then that punjabi is quite a unique language, as it&amp;rsquo;s written in two different scripts: shahmukhi (used mainly in pakistan) and gurmukhi (used mainly in india). i can understand some gurmukhi punjabi, but shahmukhi remains a mystery to me. yet, since the two scripts represent the same sounds, it should be possible to transliterate one into the other. might be worth exploring.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GREENER</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/greener/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 03:38:32 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/greener/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;greener-graph-neural-networks-for-news-media-profiling&#34;&gt;greener: graph neural networks for news media profiling&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;in the summer of 2020 i got an opportunity to work on GREENER with dr. preslav nakov and tanbih team. this project aimed at detecting bias and factuality of news media but beyond mere textual signals. in this blog post, we&amp;rsquo;ll dive into the technical details behind greener, including its methods and concepts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;problem-definition&#34;&gt;problem definition&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;greener&amp;rsquo;s goal is to profile news media outlets based on two characteristics:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graphing the Movies</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/graphing_movies/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2019 08:43:29 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/graphing_movies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;first-post&#34;&gt;First Post&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the end semester exams coming up, I figured it’s the perfect time to start my blog (yeah, great timing, right?). As I was studying Graphs for exam prep, I wanted to implement something cool using them. After searching for a while, I stumbled upon &lt;a href=&#34;https://dataverse.harvard.edu/dataset.xhtml?persistentId=doi:10.7910/DVN/T4HBA3&#34;&gt;this dataset&lt;/a&gt;. It’s from Moviegalaxies, a site that provides network graph data from around 773 films. Pretty neat, huh?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data-processing&#34;&gt;Data Processing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I took the raw data and processed it into a CSV file, showing how two characters appear together in a scene, which is represented as edges of a graph. For example, if you look at the Godfather, there are two scenes where Anthony and Michael both appear together. Here&amp;rsquo;s how it looks in the CSV format:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
